Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 1 -- Letters to Franklin 1730-1776 Mss.B.F85inventory01
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770 November to 1771 February; Mem. S. 2p.; Life, Thomas
    Account for legal services to Dr. Franklin as Agent for the Colonies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770 December 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Smith, Joseph. Burlington N.J
    Has received his favors of March 19, April 10 and 12, and June 11, and communicated them to the Committee of Correspondence, who laid them before the House of Assembly, where they gave general satisfaction. The House determined not to allow Sherwood the balance he mentions to be due him. The Committee anxious to know whether two Acts, mentioned in his letter of April 12, gained the Royal assent. Thanks him for Gov. Pownall's speech.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770 December 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Gale, Benjamin. Killingworth
    Mentioning a gold medal granted him by the Society of Arts for an improvement on the drill-plow; expresses his grateful acknowledgments to the Society for the honor they have conferred upon him. Ignorant who is Dr. Templeman's successor in the Society; sent specimen of white iron ore at the same time with his model of the drill-plow. Interest taken in the culture of mulberry trees; makes suggestions which he thinks would aid this work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770 December 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Nobel Wimberly. Savannah
    Encloses second set of bills of exchange in payment for mace and gowns. The Assembly holds in highest approbation the conduct of its Agent, and is about to pass an ordinance of reappointment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770 December 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Nobel Wimberly. Savannah
    Asking his assistance for Mr. Cornelius Winter, who intends taking holy orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770 December 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Crowley, Thomas. London
    Concerning a pamphlet by J. Otis which contains sentiments exactly similar to his own; thinks it deserves another edition; in that case, promises to take a dozen or two copies; concerned at the thought that a man of such just sentiments should have met with so much oppression.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770 December 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Tissington, Anthony. Alfreton
    His movements since July; hopes soon to return to his more pleasing studies. Glad to see by the papers that the affairs in America do well, and that Franklin settles with the Ministry, not with the Parliament. Illness of his wife. Has gathered some materials for a philosophical paper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Carburi, Count
    The Duke of Marlborough would be delighted to have Dr. Franklin at Marlborough House and see him make the experiments in electricity. Asks him if he can come and if he needs to see, beforehand, the electric machine which would be used.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770?; A.L.S. 1p.; Claphamson, Samuel. London
    Cabinet maker. Asking for the discharge of his bill delivered some time before.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1770?; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, William
    Relative to New Jersey politics and trouble with the Assembly. Threat to destroy the iron works in New Jersey as contrary to law. The Americans ought at least, before they attempt to evade this law, use all their endeavors to obtain a repeal; for the interest of both countries, that all partial Acts of that nature were abolished. His salary and expenses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, William. Perth Amboy
    Encloses a bill of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; French, Mrs Katharine
    Called at Dr. Franklin's house to invite him to dinner, to meet Mrs. Payne and to play a game of chess.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1770]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Percival, Dr Thomas. King St. London?
    Will call on Franklin in half an hour; desires his company at supper that evening.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Pringle, Sir John
    Wishes to know at what hour Dr. Franklin can meet him at Mr. Hewson's.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1770.]; L. 2p.; ------, ------
    Sends money to pay expenses of bringing certain books to his country. Asks for data of the lives of the most eminent members of the Royal Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Hawkesworth, Jno. Bromley, Kent
    Mr. Ackland is a candidate for the afternoon preachership at the Foundling Hospital; recommends him to Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 14; A.L.S. 4p.; Foxcroft, John. Philadelphia
    Introducing his brother, whom he hopes Franklin will take cordially by the hand; his brother's business in London; shares with Franklin his fondness for chess. Quite happy at hearing that there is a favorable disposition in England towards the Colonies. Trade beginning to look up; an Act to encourage and extend the trade of America would be an act of grace indeed, worthy of the British Senate, and productive of great results at the time. Concerning certain accusations made against him; their probable source; account of a conversation with Mr. Blackburn in which the latter abused Franklin; some warmth occasioned by the writer's calling himself an American; stated his belief that a good American and a good Englishman were synonymous terms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Happy to learn of his son's and brother's safe arrival. Will send to Mr. Pease for the bond and shall recover the money. Shall take pleasure to encourage his benevolent scheme. Answered his letters in regard to the lottery; decided to risk the two tickets and gave his account current credit for the balance as he directed in the past. Has not yet been able to let his house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 24; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Life, Thomas. London
    Has arranged for a conference of Dr. Franklin, Mr. Jackson and Mr. Life, for the 30th inst. in reference to the Georgia Acts. Would like a previous meeting with Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 25; L.S. M[ichael] Hillegas, Nicholas Waln and R. Strettell Jones. 1p.; The Library Company of Philadelphia. Philadelphia
    Appointed by the Directors of The Library Co. to acknowledge Franklin's favor of July 7, 1769; prevented from answering it sooner by the confusion arising from the union of the several libraries. They concur with Franklin in his opinion of the propriety of having, in some of their public libraries, all the transactions of every philosophical society in Europe; before deciding, they desire to know the price of each set and also of the French Encyclopædia. Sends catalogue of books wanted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Marshall, Humphry. West Bradford
    By all accounts the colonies have gone into the importation of goods more largely than ever; instances of great spirit, however, remaining among the farmers. Manufacture of china; of double flint glass; of silk, which, mixed with worsted, forms a material of which they make clothes. Has sent him some observations on the spots appearing on the sun's disk; asks him to show them to his old friend, John Fothergill, and after a perusal, to present them to the Royal Society, in this (Marshall's) name. Offers to furnish seeds, young plants, etc., to any gentlemen in England who may desire them, at lower prices than common; has done this work for his cousin, John Bartram, for many years.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Knox, William. London
    Encloses plan and papers in reference to the lands claimed by W[illia]m Batner's representative.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Henly, William. London
    Thanks Franklin for the improvement of his electrometers; if he has been able to produce any experiment in electricity upon which Franklin can bestow the epithet 'curious,' his highest ambition and vanity in that science is fully satisfied. Drawings and description of an experiment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 January 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Gamgius, Isaac. London
    Left Capt. Dalrymple's ship because his station was not a suitable one; hoped Franklin could have gotten a berth for him in another ship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 March 2; A.L.S. 11p.; Drage, Theodorus Swaine. Salisbury, N.C
    A long account of the religious, social and political conditions existing in his present parish.
    (Pages missing.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 March 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Nobel Wimberly. Savannah
    Informing Franklin of how their [Georgia] Assembly was dissolved by order of the Governor; same fate attended them in December, 1768. Cause for it: their having committed the Deputy Secretary, Mr. Moodie, for refusing to give evidence to the House in the case of the Deputy Surveyor-General for taking double fees in his office; this the Governor said the Assembly had no right to do. Trusts he has received the bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 March 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Nobel Wimberly. Savannah
    Sends the last two Gazettes, as they mention the matters respecting the dissolution of the Assembly referred to in his letter of the 4th inst.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 March 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Crafton, Robert. London
    Concerning an agreement to dine every Thursday at the Dog Tavern on Garlick Hill; reproaches Franklin with being there only once; expects to take the chair next Thursday and commands him, under pain of his greatest displeasure, to appear in person and bring with him several young sucking Americans, who probably attend Franklin's levees.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 March 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, Charles-Guillaume-Frédéric
    Engaged in tutoring two young Dutch noblemen; the rest of his time employed in translating Anderson's Historical and Chronological Deduction of the Origin of Commerce.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 March 30; L. 1p.; Franklin, William. Burlington
    Enclosed a letter to L.H. Heard from Mr. W. Logan that Dr. Franklin was well the first of January.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 April 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Wilson, Alexander. College, Glasgow
    Concerning some fonts of printing types; the price and quality; these terms proving agreeable, will be much obliged for orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 April 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Recommending Mr. Nicholas Biddle to Franklin's advice and assistance; the merchant service has hitherto claimed his attention but his ambition incites him to some more honorable pursuit; either the navy, or should peace continue, a berth in the East India Co.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 April 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Empson, Elizabeth. Poole
    Returning thanks for the money Franklin was kind enough to allow her; afraid that he is displeased with the freedom she has taken; her miserable situation without friends or money; disappointed that he is unable to do anything for Mr. Empson.
    [Mutilated.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 April 26; L. in 3d P.; Life, Thomas. London
    Expressing regret that owing to business of very great consequence he has not been able to wait on Franklin about the Georgia affair; makes an appointment for Monday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 April 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Keetlby, J.G. Dublin
    Question of printing-presses, forms, types, etc. An invention he has made which will alarm the whole fraternity of printers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 April 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Bartram, John. Philadelphia
    Not a line from any of his correspondents concerning the matter of the King's bounty; William Young styles himself their Majesties' botanist. His daughter, Elizabeth, has saved several thousand silk worms which she expects will hatch in a few days. His sight failing him; has handed all his business over to his son, John, except part of his garden.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 May 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Rhoads, Samuel. Philadelphia
    Limestone, — Trade of Baltimore. — Project of a canal from the Susquehanna to the Schuylkill. — Pennsylvania Hospital.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 518).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 May 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Smith, William. Philadelphia
    Agreeable to the directions of the Philosophical Society, has sent Franklin, as their President, eleven copies of the first volume of the Society's Transactions, which he is requested to deliver to the persons mentioned in the letter; will send more copies later; would like the Astronomer Royal to have his as soon as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 May 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Evans, Cadwalader. Philadelphia
    His account of Mr. Walpole's valuation of the samples of silk sent, gave them spirits; account of the condition in which the eggs arrived from Spain; advises a different manner of transportation; the experiment in American takes beyond their most sanguine expectations. Transactions of the [American Philosophical] Society sent by Dr. Smith. Departure of Gov. Penn for England immediately on hearing of his father's death; his brother, Dick Penn, who is to take his place, said to be illiterate, arbitrary and vindictive. Apologizes for not writing to [Samuel] Wharton, whose father has been ill all winter 'with a slow fever, and inveterate cough and a pertinacious refusal of all medicines'; saw a good deal of Wharton's friend, David Darrach. Sends Franklin a snuff-box made out of the root of laurel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 May 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Clarke, A. Barbadoes
    Acquainting him with their arrival on December 9; very kindly received by Capt. Clarke's mother and relations; Capt. Clarke in Grenada; his family one of the first on the island; his brother very rich and a great traveller and keeps open house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 May 7; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Pownall, Thomas. Whitehall
    Asking Franklin if he can inform him who will take out the warrant appointing [Daniel] Coxe one of the Council of New Jersey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 May 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Percival, Thomas. Manchester
    Enclosing an attempt of his to account for the different quantities of rain which fall at different heights. Hope of seeing and interviewing Franklin at Manchester.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 May 27; A.L. 4p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Has not heard from Franklin for several months. Nine numbers of the "Citizen's Ephemerides" have appeared within the last five months. Sends them to Franklin and also to Mr. Rush. His "Manual of Humanity" is finally being printed at Bouillon. His work on the "Peerage of France" has been delayed and altered by the Censor. Although the present Government is bad enough, fears a change to worse. Thinks the judges and magistrates have too much power and are more arbitrary than a despot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 May; A. Mem. 3p.; Franklin, William
    Remarks on Benjamin Franklin's account against William Franklin, dated London, April 20, 1771.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 June 1; Mem. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Joint expense account of Dr. Franklin, Mr. Canton, Dr. Ingen Housz and J. Williams, [Jr.].
  - to Dr. John Fothergill, Benjamin Franklin and David Barclay., 1771 June 3; L.S. John Reynell, Sam[ue]l Rhoads, Jam[e]s Pemberton. 2p.; The Managers of the Pennsylvania Hospital. Philadelphia
    Send them duplicates of the law and letters of attorney empowering them to receive on their account the money arising from the unclaimed shares of the Pennsylvania Land Company, also informs them that the necessities of their institution are very urgent. Ask to be informed of the receipt of money that they may embrace the very first opportunity of selling the bills of exchange which will relieve their pressing necessities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 June 11; D.S. 1p.; The Bataafsch Genootschap der Proefondervinderlijke Wijsbergeerte. Rotterdam
    Certificate of Corresponding Membership.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 June 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Crane, Stephen. Elizabethtown
    Late debate between the Governor and Assembly of New Jersey relative to the granting supplies for His Majesty's troops; reluctance on the part of the House to enter into a measure likely to pain the Governor; forced to it, however, by the inability of the inhabitants at this time to pay any additional taxes; hopes, if His Majesty insists on this tax, he will permit a bill for striking a paper currency; begs Franklin's services in obtaining this bill, which will give general satisfaction.
    [In duplicate.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 June 29; A.L. 2p.; Cushing, Thomas. Massachusetts
    His favor of February 5th was laid before the House; right of Parliament to tax the Colonies; danger of Britain's forcing a free people, by oppressive measures, into a state of desperation; Massachusetts will never submit to the authority of an absolute government.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 July 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Colden, Alexander. New York
    Has taken such steps as will put the accounts in a proper state before Mr. Foxcroft returns. Concerning an advertisement about Elizabeth Holland, and why he failed to insert it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 July 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Bond, Dr Thomas. Philadelphia
    Introducing Mr. Daniel Kheun, brother of Dr. Kheun; he goes to Sweden to study divinity, preparatory to taking charge of some Swedish congregation. His son Richard's progress in the study of physic and surgery; takes his examinations next year, and will then finish his studies in Europe; discusses the respective merits of the medical schools in Edinburgh, Paris, London, Leyden and Vienna; would like Sir John Pringle's advice on this matter. Thanking Franklin for a new picture, a striking likeness of himself, presented to him by good Mrs. Franklin. On June 28 had a commencement in the College; the farce prettily played. Certain medical dissertations. A correspondence with the learned societies of Europe would prove an advantage to the [American] Philosophical Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 July 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Jones, Nobel Wimberly. Savannah
    Amazed that the objection to Mr. Winter's ordination was his regard for or connection with Mr. Whitefield. Concerning what Franklin mentions from Mr. Manduit relative to the dissenters. The Governor's reasons for dissolving the first Assembly; personal enmity against himself. Franklin's solicitations on behalf of the Negro law will be gratefully acknowledged by every well-wisher to the Province. Hopes all difficulties will be overcome respecting Sir William Baker's claim; warns him not to count on the Governor's assistance. Wishes Franklin had written to the Committee of Correspondence relative to public matters. As they were not dissolved with the House as Franklin imagined, his letters containing some matters of a private nature, he did not choose to send to them, and some of the Committee being those that assisted the Governor in using him (Jones) ill, he could not well in person communicate them; however he will contrive some method to acquaint them with what they have a right to know.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 July 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Zubly, John Joachim. Savannah
    Finds that Mr. Jasper Mauduit has applied for Franklin's kind assistance to remove some grievances imposed on protestant dissenters; dispute between himself and the rector; encloses copy of letter published on that occassion; question of sexton's fees. Bill sent by the upper house to the lower, in which a rate is fixed on all dissenters to be paid to the rector, though his attendance is not required nor any duty performed; this received not a vote in the lower house. Refusal of upper house to hear a second reading of a bill passed in the lower to lay out a burying ground for protestant dissenters; expects a like bill in favor of the Jews will meet with the same fate. Unlucky in being a dissenter in political as well as religious matters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 July 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Arrival in town of Mr. Foxcroft and his lady.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 July 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Whitehurst, John. London
    Hopes Franklin will be pleased with the two clocks he sent; had not time to engrave the plates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Whitehurst, John. Derby
    Sends the bill for the clocks; the other one Franklin was kind enough to order will soon be completed; alteration he deemed necessary to make in Mr. Ferguson's plan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William. Burlington
    Just returned from Philadelphia where he has been for some days with Betsy in order to see her brother Downes, his wife and daughter, who arrived there from Barbadoes; he is in bad health, so took him home with them to escape the heat of Philadelphia. Sally's [Mrs. Bache] determination to accompany her husband to England in the fall; thinks the expense of such a trip will not suit Mr. Bache's present circumstances nor consistent with justice to his creditors; if she does go, wishes his mother might have some clever body to take care of her; her memory has failed much; daily becomes more unfit to be left alone.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 August 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Settlement of accounts. News of the family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 August 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Colden, Alexander. New York
    Has lost Mr. Jesser's letter. Enclosing the second set of those bills, sent by Mr. Foxcroft by the last packet; Mr. Foxcroft and Lady both well. Gov. Tryon has arrived and taken the administration of the government; his amiable disposition promises good things; Lord Dunmore has sent his seals and baggage to Virginia, but is at present on a tour to Lake Champlain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1771] August 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Shipley, Jonathan
    Desiring Franklin to deliver his letters to Primate and Mrs. Jackson; his loss keenly felt at Twyford. Concerning the probable behavior of his younger daughter, Franklin's fellow-traveler.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 September 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    His belief that Hall will pay the money. Franklin's kindness to his sons; glad Josiah is remaining in London; safe arrival of Jonathan, who is just entering into business in Boston. Question of an indorsement of Franklin's bond, received by John Cooke.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 October 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Holt, John. New York
    A true account of an unhappy difference between his neighbor, Mr. Hugh Hughes and his brother John; the cause was the espousal of the Stamp Act by Mr. John Hughes; his haughty and imperious character. Unhappy situation of Mr. Hugh Hughes' affairs; by being security he became insolvent; for years made himself a voluntary prisoner in his own house to avoid arrest; supported a numerous family by teaching school; his health impaired; anxious to get some other occupation; offers of assistance from his brother, such as no man of spirit could accept.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 October 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Cushing, Thomas. Boston
    William Storey will deliver to Franklin the votes of the last sessions of the General Court. Account of a difficulty Mr. Storey is in; took Mr. Wheelwright's note of hand at the direction of the Surveyor-General; Mr. Wheelwright's subsequent failure; Mr. Storey goes to England to apply for relief to the Commissioners there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 October 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Concerning certain bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 October 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Clay, Ann. Newcastle
    Recommending her son to Franklin. Has been a widow four years; is neither rich nor poor; has eleven children, which she regards as an addition to her happiness. If necessary, begs him to advance 200 guineas to her son, for the payment of which she will be his security.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 October 7; L. 1p.; Henly, William